William Maxwell Evarts Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Maxwell Evarts Papers 1667-1918 (bulk 1877-1891)
MSS20032
Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901
12,500 items
61 containers plus 1 oversize
12.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, United States senator from New York, and United States secretary of state and attorney general. Correspondence, diary, journal, account books, minute book, printed material, drafts of memoranda, and a journal of college reading relating mainly to New York state, national, and international politics from the Civil War to the 1890s.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916--Correspondence.; Astor, John Jacob, 1822-1890--Correspondence.; Bates, Edward, 1793-1869--Correspondence.; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893--Correspondence.; Choate, Joseph Hodges, 1832-1917--Correspondence.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Trials, litigation, etc.; Evarts, William Maxwell, 1818-1901.; Field, Cyrus W. (Cyrus West), 1819-1892--Correspondence.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881--Correspondence.; Hay, John, 1838-1905--Correspondence.; Hoar, E. R. (Ebenezer Rockwood), 1816-1895--Correspondence.; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875--Impeachment.; Morton, Levi P. (Levi Parsons), 1824-1920--Correspondence.; Phelps, Edward John, 1822-1900--Correspondence.; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872--Correspondence.; Tilden, Samuel J. (Samuel Jones), 1814-1886.; Trescot, William Henry, 1822-1898--Correspondence.; Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820-1889--Correspondence.; Winthrop, Robert C. (Robert Charles), 1809-1894--Correspondence.
Organizations
Geneva Arbitration Tribunal.; International Monetary Conference (1878: Paris, France); Peabody Education Fund.; United States. Department of Justice. Office of the Attorney General.; United States. Department of State.
Subjects
Bimetallism.; Diplomatic and consular service, American.; Emigration and immigration law--United States.; Patronage, Political--United States.; Pensions--United States.; Practice of law--New York (State); Presidents--United States--Election--1876.; Presidents--United States--Election--1880.; Statue of Liberty (New York, N.Y.); Statues--New York (State)--New York.; Suffrage--United States.; Tariff--United States.
Places
China--Emigration and immigration.; New York (State)--Politics and government--1865-1950.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Foreign relations--1865-1898.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Claims.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Lawyers.; Senators, U.S. Congress--New York (State)
Provenance
The papers of William Maxwell Evarts, lawyer, United States senator from New York, and United States secretary of state and attorney general, were deposited in the Library of Congress, 1939-1942, by Effingham Evarts, and converted to a gift in 1943. Additions were purchased in 1965 and 1986.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Maxwell Evarts are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1818, Feb. 6 Born, Boston, Mass.
1833 1837 Attended Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1836 Cofounder of Yale Literary Magazine
1837 Read law, office of Horace Everett, Windsor, Vt.
1841 Admitted to the bar in New York Began law practice
1843 Married Helen Minerva Wardner
1849 1853 Assistant district attorney, Southern District of New York
1860 Delegate to Republican national convention, Chicago, Ill.
1863 Sent to England by United States to help prevent equipping of the Confederate navy by the British
1868 Counsel for the defense, impeachment trial of Andrew Johnson
1868 1869 Attorney general
1872 Represented the United States in Alabama claims case, Geneva, Switzerland
1877 Chief counsel for Republican Party, Hayes-Tilden presidential election dispute
1877 1881 Secretary of state
1881 Delegate, International Monetary Conference, Paris, France
1885 1891 United States senator from New York
1901, Feb. 28 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Maxwell Evarts (1818-1901) span the years 1667-1918 with the bulk of the material dated 1877-1891. They consist of correspondence, a diary, certificates, genealogical material, indexes, a notebook, dockets, memoranda, letterbooks, account books, minute book, printed matter, financial material, and a journal. The bulk of the collection relates to Evarts's tenure as secretary of state, 1877-1881, and United States senator, 1885-1891.
The focus of the collection is on New York state and national politics and international affairs in which Evarts participated. Main topics include Evarts's early law practice, cases in which he represented the United States during the Civil War, the trial of Jefferson Davis, impeachment of Andrew Johnson, the Geneva Arbitration Tribunal of 1871-1872, the election of 1876, appointment of ambassadors, Chinese immigration, presidential campaign of 1880, International Monetary Conference of 1878, the Peabody education fund, dedication of the Statue of Liberty, patronage, suffrage, pensions, tariffs, and the Force Bill that provided for the collection of duties on imported goods.
Correspondents include James Burrill Angell, John Jacob Astor, Edward Bates, James Gillespie Blaine, Joseph Hodges Choate, Cyrus W. Field, James A. Garfield, John Hay, Ebenezer Rockwood Hoar, Levi P. Morton, Edward John Phelps, William H. Seward, William Henry Trescot, Julia Gardiner Tyler, and Robert C. Winthrop.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Bound Correspondence and Other Documents, 1842-1908
Miscellany, 1667-1918
Oversize, 1877-1879
Container List
- Bound Correspondence and Other Documents, 1842-1908 (Box 1-54)
  Correspondence and other documents.
  Arranged chronologically in bound volumes.
  - 1842, Jan. 26-1872, June 20 (Box 1)
  - 1872, June 22-Oct. 12 (Box 2)
  - 1872, Oct. 14-1874, June 10 (Box 3)
  - 1874, Dec. 16-1877, Mar. 11 (Box 4)
  - 1877 (Box 5)
    - Mar. 12-Apr. 5 (Box 5)
    - Apr. 6-June 4 (Box 6)
    - June 5-July 8 (Box 7)
    - July 9-Sept. 6 (Box 8)
    - Sept. 7-Oct. 20 (Box 9)
    - Oct. 22-Dec. 7 (Box 10)
  - 1877, Dec. 8-1878, Jan. 18 (Box 11)
  - 1878 (Box 12)
    - Jan. 19-Feb. 21 (Box 12)
    - Feb. 22-Apr. 7 (Box 13)
    - Apr. 8-May 24 (Box 14)
    - May 25-June 27 (Box 15)
  - 1878 (Box 16)
    - June 28-Aug. 14 (Box 16)
    - Aug. 15-Oct. 15 (Box 17)
    - Oct. 17-Dec. 2 (Box 18)
  - 1878, Dec. 3-1879, Jan. 24 (Box 19)
  - 1879 (Box 20)
    - Jan. 25-Mar. 11 (Box 20)
    - Mar. 12-Apr. 30 (Box 21)
    - May 1-June 17 (Box 22)
    - June 19-Aug. 25 (Box 23)
    - Aug. 2-Nov. 5 (Box 24)
  - 1879, Nov. 6-1880, Jan. 3 (Box 25)
  - 1880 (Box 26)
    - Jan. 4-Feb. 19 (Box 26)
    - Feb. 20-May 6 (Box 27)
  - 1880, May 7-1881, Jan. 11 (Box 28)
  - 1881, Jan. 17-1882, Jan. 28 (Box 29)
  - 1882, Jan. 29-Nov. 25 (Box 30)
  - 1882, Dec. 9-1884, Mar. 10 (Box 31)
  - 1884, Mar. 13-1885, Jan. 17 (Box 32)
  - 1885 (Box 33)
    - Jan. 21-Apr. 23 (Box 33)
    - Apr. 25-Dec. 18 (Box 34)
  - 1885, Dec. 21-1886, Jan. 22 (Box 35)
  - 1886 (Box 36)
    - Jan. 23-Mar. 1 (Box 36)
    - Mar. 2-Apr. 20 (Box 37)
    - Apr. 21-May 28 (Box 38)
    - May 29-Aug. 13 (Box 39)
    - Aug. 20-Dec. 30 (Box 40)
  - 1886, Dec. 31-1887, Jan. 18 (Box 41)
  - 1887 (Box 42)
    - Jan. 19-Feb. 3 (Box 42)
    - Feb. 4-Feb. 17 (Box 43)
    - Feb. 18- Mar. 18 (Box 44)
  - 1887, Mar. 23-1890, July 17 (Box 45)
  - 1890, July 19-Nov. 23 (Box 46)
  - 1890, Nov. 26-1891, Feb. 3 (Box 47)
  - 1891 (Box 48)
    - Feb. 4-Mar. 22 (Box 48)
    - Mar. 23-May 14 (Box 49)
    - May 15-July 13 (Box 50)
    - July 15-Sept. 12 (Box 51)
    - Sept. 14-Nov. 28 (Box 52)
  - 1891, Nov. 29-1897, Feb. 5 (Box 53)
  - 1897, Feb. 6-1908, Nov. 16 (Box 54)
- Miscellany, 1667-1918 (Box 55-62)
  Correspondence, a diary, certificates, genealogical material, indexes, a notebook, dockets, memoranda, letterbooks, account books, minute book, printed matter, financial material, and a journal.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Account books and checkbooks, 1872-1880, undated (Box 55)
  - Certificates, 1877-1879 See Oversize (Box 55)
  - Clippings, 1877-1891, undated (Box 55)
  - Dockets, 1877-1891, (3 folders) (Box 55)
  - Family correspondence, 1829, 1839 (Box 55)
  - Genealogical material, 1893, undated (Box 55)
  - General correspondence, 1852-1889, 1896 (?), 1918, undated, (11 folders) (Box 56)
  - Grant Monument Fund, account book, 1892-1900 (Box 56)
  - Indexes, undated, (4 folders) (Box 57)
  - Journals (Box 57)
    - 1834 (Box 57)
    - 1863 (Box 58)
  - Letterbooks (Box 58)
    - 1877, May 22-1878, May 20, (2 folders) (Box 58)
    - 1879, May 10-1881, Mar. 2, (2 folders) (Box 59)
  - Leupp, Charles M., estate, 1859-1877 (Box 59)
  - Minutes, first meeting of the Board of Trustees, New York and Northern Land and Improvement Co., Sherman Evarts, secretary, 1889 (Box 59)
  - Miscellany, 1667, 1863-1891, undated, (3 folders) (Box 60)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 60)
  - Printed matter (Box 60)
    - 1835, 1861-1872 (Box 60)
    - 1873-1892, (6 folders) (Box 61)
    - Undated (Box 62)
  - Register of documents sent, Forty-ninth Congress, 1886-1887 (Box 62)
  - Republican Territorial Central Committee, 1872-1878 (Box 62)
- Oversize, 1877-1879 (Box OV 1)
  Certificates.
  Arranged and described according to the series, folders, and containers from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Certificates, 1877-1879 (Container 55) (Box OV 1)